Hey there, it's me.
Welcome back to our lesson on paragraph building.
This is a magical lesson because it will help us build an effective paragraph with a logical structure.
To prove this, I'll share with you two magical spells, TFS.
Once you understand what they are and apply them effectively, your paragraphs
will become clearer and more logical than ever.
Now let's start our today's lesson on how to build effective paragraph structures for Task 2.
Our lesson is divided into three parts.
Part 1, Paragraph Structure, T.
Part 2, Paragraph Structure, FS.
And Part 3, Practice.
To achieve two goals, help you remember and understand some features of two paragraph structures, T and FS,
and apply this knowledge to organize ideas and build effective paragraphs.
Make sure you have your notes ready.
Here we go.
Do you remember the paragraph in the previous lesson?
Today we still use that paragraph to learn about the structure of an effective paragraph.
Through this, I want you to try unlocking the T spell following
two steps.
Step 1, identify the function of each sentence in the paragraph.
We've done this step very carefully in the previous lesson.
Now try to do it yourself to see if you remember what you learned.
Step 2, based on the position of each sentence in the paragraph,
conclude the T structure.
You will have two minutes.
Please pause the video to read the paragraph and do this task.
Let's do it.
Okay, and here is the answer for step 1.
Now get ready to answer the following question.
You finished it all, right?
In this paragraph, the first sentence is the topic sentence.
The next one is an explanation explaining the main idea of the
topic sentence and followed by a sentence that explains it more clearly,
which is also an explanation.
Coming to the next sentence, this one supports the previous sentence by
giving an example.
Then, the example is added with more details by the last sentence
or elaboration.
That's right, the T structure is short for topic sentence, explanation,
example, elaboration, in which a topic sentence carries the main idea of
the whole paragraph.
Following the deductive writing method, this sentence is usually at the
beginning of the paragraph.
An explanation explains and supports the topic sentence.
An example gives specific cases to support the explanation.
An elaboration adds more details to the previous explanation or example.
In fact, in this structure, only the topic sentence is a fixed
part that must be in that position.
The three E's are quite flexible.
Therefore, this group of sentences can be organized in different ways.
It can be explanation, example, elaboration or explanation, elaboration, example.
This means you give an explanation and support it with an elaboration,
then continue with a simple example to illustrate the elaboration.
It can also be example, explanation, elaboration.
This means you give an example first and support it with an
explanation, then add more details to this explanation by an elaboration.
It can also be explanation, elaboration, example, elaboration or TEEE, just
like in the sample paragraph above.
It doesn't matter.
The term T is just to represent what we need to include in the paragraph.
The order or number of sentences doesn't matter.
However, we have to make sure that paragraphs following the TEEE structure
only focus on one explanation, explain and give examples for it, no
matter how many sentences are written.
However, under the time pressure in the IELTS exam room, you should
only write a maximum of six to seven sentences for each paragraph.
Time management is very important.
The two functions explanation and example must be included in the paragraph.
This method of writing a paragraph is easy to understand and coherent,
but it's not the only way.
And for some people, it might not be the easiest to write.
Now let's learn another paragraph structure through the sample from the previous lesson.
Now let's compare the structure of this paragraph with the TEEE structure
and answer the following two questions.
Let's pause the video for about five minutes to do this task.
Compare and analyze the components in the two paragraphs, then find out the answer.
See you in a bit.
First of all, both paragraphs have a topic sentence at the beginning.
This is the basic rule of writing paragraphs, so there's nothing more
to discuss here.
Two functions, explanation and example.
Although the number of sentences is different, they still meet this requirement.
Meanwhile, the differences are, While the paragraph following the TEEE
structure has only one explanation, and it is explained in detail by
this elaboration, the paragraph following the FS structure has two
explanations.
While the paragraph following the TEEE structure has only one example, and
it is explained in detail by this elaboration, the paragraph following the
FS structure has two examples.
So, the TEEE and FS structures are different when it comes to
how many explanations and examples they include.
Alright, at this point, can you guess what FS is short for?
Here's a hint.
The two words have already appeared in the paragraph.
That's right.
It is firstly and secondly.
FS stands for two words representing the two explanations in the paragraph,
which is the biggest difference between the FS structure and the TEEE structure.
There are two things to remember when using the FS structure.
Firstly and secondly are just two words representing two explanations, and you
don't need to use exactly these words in your paragraph.
You can use some synonyms of these two words, such as to
begin with or in addition to replace them.
The FS structure must have two explanations, and they need to be
explained and illustrated.
However, each explanation does not necessarily have an accompanying example.
The first explanation may have both elaboration and example, while the second
one may have one of the two, as long as throughout the
paragraph it has both functions of explanation and example.
Our sample paragraph is well structured with two examples for both ideas,
but it's acceptable to write only one elaboration for the second TEEE
without an example, as long as it's explained clearly to persuade the reader.
By now, I hope you've understood the features of the two structures,
TEEE and FS, as well as their similarities and differences, so that
you can choose which is suitable for you when writing paragraphs.
Now, let's practice a bit, shall we?
Good job everyone!
We've done an excellent job, which is to overcome a challenging but
very important lesson in the process of building paragraphs.
After the past minutes, we've achieved the goals.
Remember and understand some features of two paragraph structures, TEEE and FS,
and apply this knowledge to organize ideas and build effective paragraphs.
Goodbye, and I'll see you soon in the next lesson.